Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2013; 64 Gigabytes (87 video and text files)
  - Robin McHaelen interviewed by Julie Maynard, 2013 March 30; McHaelen, Robin; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Robin McHaelen (b. 1955) grew up in Waterbury and Wolcott, Connecticut, and graduated from the University of Connecticut in 1994 with a Masters of Social Work. She is the founder and executive director of True Colors Inc. Sexual Minority Youth and Family Services, a non-profit organization that "works to create a world where youth of all sexual orientations and gender identities are valued and affirmed." The organization hosts a conference each March that features LGBT resources and workshops and is open to all interested parties, including youth and educators. True Colors, previously named Children From the Shadows, was started in 1992. McHaelen also provides training and courses for schools, The Department of Children and Families and mental health professionals. She lives in Manchester, Connecticut, with her wife, Holly Lawrence McHaelen, and daughter, Rhylie, 14. Lawrence got her Masters of Social Work along with McHaelen, and home-schools Rhylie.
    In this oral history, Robin McHaelen describes a childhood of isolation which she associates with her gay identity and the effect that has had on her life, particularly on her social activism. She also paints a vivid picture of her Italian family, which she characterizes as central to her identity. McHaelen speaks talks about how she came to the University of Connecticut's School of Social Work and her involvement with Children From the Shadows. She shares stories about True Color's transformation from a fieldwork project to a non-profit organization with a substantially wider reach. McHaelen reflects on her life as an activist, particularly her efforts to reach out to more people and about how she has work to keep from getting burnt out in this demanding work. She describes the critical importance of her experience as a wife and mother, recounting heartfelt stories that reflect an evident pride in her daughter. The conversation includes her personal journey with her own sexuality and therapy, her coming out as a lesbian at her job, her reflections about lesbian history, especially lesbian book stores and women's music festivals, as well as her identity as a "recovering Catholic."
    McHaelen, Robin
    - Video interview of Robin McHaelen
    - Transcript of interview of Robin McHaelen (Box 1)
  - Alice O'Donovan interviewed by Megan G. Yeo, 2013 March 8; O'Donovan, Alice; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Alice L. O'Donovan (b. 1945) was born Alice Louise Lilly to Kathryn Frisbie Lilly and Ralph Guilford Lilly in Plattsburg, New York. She was raised in Willsboro, New York until age nine and in Ashfield, Massachusetts until age seventeen and attended high school at Sanderson Academy in Ashfield, Massachusetts, graduating in 1963. Her one brother was born in 1935. O'Donovan's father, Ralph Lilly received a BA from Middlebury College and and MA from Columbia University. He worked as an educator, school administrator and banker. Kathryn Lilly received her BA from Adelphi College and was a full time educator before her marriage. She worked part time as a substitute teacher while raising her children. O'Donovan earned a Bachelor of Science in recreation administration from the University of Massachusetts, followed by a Masters of Divinity from Episcopal Divinity School, Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1988, and a Master of Arts in Religious Studies from Hartford Seminary, Hartford, Connecticut in 1988. She married Robert J. O'Donovan Sr. in 1971 and divorced in 1982. He died in 2004. She has three children from this marriage, Robert Jr., Stephen, and Mary. O'Donovan worked as a field director for the Connecticut Trails Council of Girl Scouts from 1967 to 1970 and became the first female director of recreation for the City of Norwich, Connecticut in 1970. Additional experiences include farm laborer, fire department EMT and chaplain, and member of a town library board. Since 1988, she was employed in several pastoral positions at Peru Congregational Church in Peru, Vermont, South Windham Congregational Church; as Interim Associate Pastor at the Congregational Church of South Glastonbury; Interim Pastor at the United Church in Bernardston, Massachusetts; Interim Pastor at Second Congregational Church of Stafford at West Stafford and Interim Pastor at Westfield Congregational Church in Danielson, Connecticut until September 2012. O'Donovan has worked tom raise awareness within church organizations around lesbian/gay issues since 1982 as a member of the United Church Coalition for Lesbian/Gay Concerns. O'Donovan lives in Tolland, CT with her partner Kathleen (Cass) Crewdson. Crewdson and O'Donovan met in 1970 as colleagues on a summer camp staff, began their life together in 1980 and were legally married in 2009 on their 25th anniversary. Cass earned a BS at the University of Nebraska at Lincoln, attended graduate school at the Connecticut Center for Message Therapy, and is a Licensed Massage Therapist. O'Donovan identifies as a Caucasian, lower-middle-class lesbian and as a Christian in the United Church of Christ.
    In this oral history, O'Donovan tells about her family and parental background in New England in the 1950s and 60s. She recalls leading a happy childhood as a tomboy fascinated with outdoor sports, bicycles, horses TV, Girl Scouts and reading books and refers to her early, independent interest in religion and church. The interview includes a wide range of her interests, and traces a trajectory from college to seminary during the 1970s. She talks about shifts from Southern Baptist to Roman Catholic and finally to United Church of Christ and Congregational Church denominations. O'Donovan reflects on her sexual identity, her relationship with her partner, Cass, and outlines the dynamics of her divorce, as she left her husband to raise three kids with Cass. She discusses historically significant ordination as the first openly gay women ordained by the Episcopal Church in Connecticut in 1980 and the hardships and victories of her church life, including struggles with discrimination as well as acceptance in her churches. Through pastoral leadership and membership in the United Church Coalition for Lesbian/Gay Concerns, O'Donovan utilized her self-identity as a "justice pastor" to further an understanding of lesbian and gay issues in her congregations through a lens of faith.
    O'Donovan, Alice
    - Video interview of Alice O'Donovan
    - Transcript of interview of Alice O'Donovan (Box 1)
  - David Perez interviewed by Rachel Klinger, 2013-03-22; Perez, David; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    David Perez (b.1961) grew up in Northampton, Massachusetts and attended Northampton High School. He has two older brothers and a younger sister. Both of his parents emigrated to the United Stated from Puerto Rico in the 1950s. Perez married his wife Michelle in 1985 and their son Derek was born in 1986. His mother, father, brother, brother-in-law, sister-in-law and David have all worked for Smith College. At the time of this interview, Perez had just completed his 30th year of service as a custodian at Smith. He was the assistant coach for the Smith basketball team from 2000-2007. Perez and his wife share a two-family home with his brother and sister-in-law in Florence, Massachusetts.
    In this oral history, Perez talks about how his family came to the United States and, specifically, to Northampton. He talks briefly about his parents and their work on tobacco fields in Sunderland, Massachusetts. The interview focuses on the changing face of Northampton, particularly on shifting class dynamics and other shifts since the 1980s. Perez speaks about the lessening of homophobia he has observed in Northampton, and his own growing awareness of the lesbian community at Smith, as well as his recent identification with pan-sexuality and the misreading of his gender. He also speaks about his experiences as the assistant coach of the basketball team at Smith, his operatic voice lessons, AIDS, racism in Northampton High and his mentorship of a transboy through Facebook. The oral history traces Perez's work history from employment in a car showroom to the Daily Hampshire Gazette and then to Smith College.
    Perez, David
    - Video interview of David Perez
    - Transcript of interview of David Perez (Box 1)
  - Carol Queen interviewed by Parks Dunlap, 2013 April 9; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    - Video interview of Carol Queen
    - Transcript of interview of Carol Queen (Box 1)
  - Kelly Rees interviewed by Carolyn Rees, 2013 March 19; Rees, Kelly; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Kelly Rees was born in Colombus, Ohio in 1966, the sixth of seven siblings, and grew up in Wilkinsburg, Pennsylvania, a racially diverse borough of Pittsburgh that began to decline economically with high unemployment and the shutting down of steel mills, increased racial tension, "white flight", and declining housing values. She went to Catholic school for twelve years and received her Associates Degree in Nursing in 1989. Rees has lived in Pittsburgh for the entirety of her life. She came out as a lesbian at the age of 17. She is a registered nurse, but was unemployed at the time of this interview.
    In her oral history, Kelly Rees describes her childhood in Wilkinsburg, Pennsylvania and her family of seven siblings. She discusses her relationship with her parents and the process of coming out as a teenager in Wilkinsburg. She discusses the gay community in Pittsburgh, its small size, and the butch/femme dynamics that she observed. She describes the bar scene in Pittsburgh during the 1980s as well as where LGBTQ spaces are emerging today in the city. She shares her insights and values, emphasizing honesty and truthfulness in response to ignorance and lack of forgiveness.
    Rees, Kelly
    - Video interview of Kelly Rees
    - Transcript of interview of Kelly Rees (Box 1)
  - Renee Ruffino interviewed by Monica Muñoz, 2013 March 21; Ruffino, Renee; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Renee Ruffino (b. 1957) was born, raised and currently lives in Buffalo, New York. She has held various jobs throughout her life, from shoes salesperson to working at a printing company, and eventually as creative design director and adjunct professor at the University at Buffalo. In between, she earned her MFA from the University at Buffalo. Ruffino lives with her life partner, Sherri Darrow, and together they have raised three children, one biological and two of Ruffino's nieces. Ruffino is highly involved in the Buffalo community, as a principal in various art galleries as well as several organizations in Buffalo. She has a passion for art and photography.
    In this oral history, Renee Ruffino describes her childhood growing up in an Italian-American working-class family and community. She talks about attending the University at Buffalo and the various jobs she has held throughout her life. Ruffino reflects on her coming out process and her experiences in the lesbian bar scene in Buffalo, where she met her partner, Sherri Darrow. She discusses the creation and growth of her family, including having one child together and taking in two of her nieces. In addition, this interview details her relationship to art, religion, and to the Buffalo community. Ruffino describes her relationship to her four siblings and the recent death of one of her sisters. Her story documents the changes she has seen in the lesbian/gay community in Buffalo over time and explores nuanced details of her life as a lesbian in Buffalo, New York.
    Ruffino, Renee
    - Video interview of Renee Ruffino
      AV and unedited video unavailable.
    - Transcript of interview of Renee Ruffino (Box 1)
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, Spring 2014, 0.75 linear feet (1 full letter box, 1 half letter box; closed files in a third box shared with 2015-S-0068); 39 Gigabytes (60 digital video and text files)
  - Dana Beyer interviewed by Megan Haaga, 2014 March 18; 1 oral histories
    Dana Beyer (b. 1952) grew up in New York City and graduated from Cornell University Phi Beta Kappa in 1974 and from University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine in 1978. Beyer worked as a physician and eye surgeon in Kenya, Washington, D.C., Florida, Nepal, and Mississippi. She retired from clinical practice in 1990 and has been living in Chevy Chase, Maryland, devoting her time to her two sons, earning a master's degree in organic chemistry, and participating in extensive political activism. Beyer ran for Maryland state senate in 2006 and 2010 while serving as a Montgomery County Council staffer, and is currently (in 2014) campaigning again. If elected, she would be the first transgender state delegate in the United States, and one of very few openly transgender elected officials in the world. Beyer has been a leader in many local and national organizations, including Gender Rights Maryland, the Democratic National Convention Rules Committee, Teachthefacts.org, Equality Maryland, Progressive Neighbors, Human Rights Campaign, and National Center for Transgender Equality. Her activism includes bringing comprehensive sex education to Montgomery County public schools, working to pass an artificial trans fats ban in Montgomery County as a County Council staffer, lobbying to pass gender identity anti-discrimination laws in three Maryland counties, and helping to re-write the DSM in 2012 so that being transgender is no longer considered a mental illness. Beyer also reaches a wider audience through writing a weekly column for the Huffington Post.
    In this oral history, Dana Beyer describes her childhood in a Jewish family in New York City in the 1950s and her intense focus on her education. The interview largely traces Beyer's life through her gender identity and how being closeted for so long impacted her life in many ways, from her relationships with her parents, two ex-wives, and two sons, to her choice of medical specialty, to her introverted yet risk-taking personality. Beyer's story moves through realizing she was a girl as a young child in the late 1950s, experiencing trauma and medical mistreatment from an intersex complication as a teenager in the 1960s, witnessing the 1969 Stonewall Rebellion from the closet, traveling the world for her medical career in the late 1970s/early 1980s, learning about successful trans women like Lynn Conway and the possibilities of surgeries in the 1980s, beginning the transition process in the 1990s, and fully coming out as Dana in the early 2000s, after the catalyst of the 9/11 attacks in 2001. Beyer reflects on transphobia and assimilation in the queer community, the rewards and challenges of activism, shifts in sexual orientation labels, and differences and parallels between the Boomer and Millennial generations. Her story shows how she used her experiences of trauma and compartmentalization to fuel her surgical and activist careers.
    - Video interview of Dana Beyer
    - Transcript of interview of Dana Beyer (Box 1)
  - Penny Coleman interviewed by Suri Roth-Katz, 2014 March 23; 1 oral histories
    Penny Coleman (b. 1948) grew up on Long Island, graduated from Vassar in 1970, and received a Bachelor's of Photographic Arts from Brooks Institute of Photography in 1974 and a Master's in Social Policy from Empire State SUNY in 1996. Coleman's career as a photographer spans employment at various newspapers including the New York Times, the LA Times and the Dallas Morning News. She is the author of two books, Village Elders and Flashback: Posttraumatic Stress Disorder, Suicide, and the Lessons of War. In addition to the publication of her second book, Coleman has written numerous articles on veterans' issues and spoke before the House of Representatives Veterans Affairs Committee on the topic of suicide among veterans. She is currently the program director of the Graduate Certificate Program in Veteran Services at Empire State.
    In this oral history Penny Coleman describes her childhood on Long Island, including the experience of being the child of liberals in a very racist and segregated community and her growing awareness of social injustices which would shape the work she has done throughout her life. This interview focuses on the parts of Coleman's life that have led her to write her two books, both of which work towards elevating the voices of marginal communities. Her marriages, first to a Vietnam veteran who took his own life, and the current one to a professor at Empire State, have been central to the work she does as a political activist. Her activism draws on her skills as a photographer and journalist as well as her position as a member of the LGBTQ community and the military community. Coleman's recollections of the oral history work she did in order to write Village Elders and again to write Flashback reflect on the importance of oral history practices and how she has used them in her efforts to fight injustice.
    - Video interview of Penny Coleman
    - Transcript of interview of Penny Coleman (Box 1)
  - Geri DiNardo interviewed by Catherine Cote, 2014 March 8; 1 oral histories
    This interview is available for research. Sections have been removed from the final transcript and the unedited transcript is not included. Edited video is available.
    Geri (Geraldine) DiNardo (b. 1943) graduated high school from St. Mary's in Milford, MA and moved on to graduate from Our Lady of the Elms in Chicopee, MA, in 1964. She received a Masters in Education from Worcester State College and went on to teach in Spencer and Worcester public schools. She was involved with Catholic Charities, and for fifteen years, she worked for the Division of Mental Health. Geri has been associated with the Catholic Worker Movement and the Worcester Mustard Seed since their beginning.
    In this oral history, Geri discusses issues of growing up as a lesbian in a heterosexual world. Due to her lack of awareness of lesbianism, she only first identified as a lesbian at the age of 70. Geri has had relationships with women throughout her adult life, and speaks about the intersection of her sexuality with her staunch Catholic faith. She talks about her growing frustration with intolerant Church doctrine, which caused her to speak out at age 70, writing in to a local Catholic Worker newsletter and identifying herself as a lesbian. Geri has since been involved in her local PFLAG. She strongly urges that LGBT Catholics should not leave the Church and discusses her involvement in the Worcester Mustard Seed.
    - Transcript of interview of Geri DiNardo (Box 1)
  - L. Orrell (pseudonym) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 March 19; 1 oral histories
    L. Orrell (b. 1962) grew up in Ellicott City, Maryland and various parts of New Mexico. As a young adult, Orrell lived in Dallas, Texas; Columbus, Ohio; and Lynn, Massachusetts. During this time she worked various jobs and participated in local lesbian and gay social scenes. Orrell moved to Weston, Massachusetts to care for her aging grandmother in 1984. Through their relationship and the location of Weston, she began to pursue a growing interest in horticulture, eventually resulting in her engagement in higher education and completion of a B.S. and M.S. in environmental biology. She pursued advanced degrees in environmental biology, completing a Ph.D. program in 2006. Throughout this time, Orrell ran her own landscaping business, taught as a grad student, married, divorced her partner/wife of 20 years, farmed the land, and raised two children.
    In this oral history L. Orrell describes her childhood in a middle class neighborhood in Ellicott City, Maryland in the 1960s. Orrell then describes her experiences moving to small-town New Mexico as a young teenager, her experiences at the Cambridge School of Weston in the 1970s, and her subsequent move back to New Mexico after being pulled out of school. Situating her teenage years in the 1970s, Orrell discusses her developing lesbian sexuality, her attraction to women, and her engagement with "sex, drugs, and rock 'n' roll" during this time. The second half of the interview is focused on her life as a young adult. Orrell moved to multiple states with different lovers, eventually settling in Weston, MA to care for her aging grandmother. The focus of this part of the interview is on her developing passion for horticulture, which led her to begin college and pursue degrees in environmental biology. In this period of her life, Orrell met and married her partner/wife with whom she raised two children. Orrell reflects on her marriage and divorce extensively in the final forty minutes of the interview, discussing internalized homophobia and difficulties of lesbian parenting as issues that emerged during the relationship. Orrell ends with a small discussion of her current partner, who was her best friend before they were romantically involved.
    - Transcript of interview of L. Orrell (Box 1)
      Interview may not be placed online. Access agreement required.
  - Sharon Fagan interviewed by Amanda Lewis, 2014 April 13; 1 oral histories
    - Video interview of Sharon Fagan
    - Transcript of interview of Sharon Fagan (Box 3)
  - Vicki Gabriner interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 March 15; 1 oral histories
    Vicki Gabriner (b. 1942) was born in Brooklyn, New York, where both of her parents were foreign language teachers in public schools. She attended Cornell University and moved on to the University of Wisconsin, at which point she spent her summers doing voter registration work in Atlanta. After receiving a master's degree in education in 1978 she moved to Atlanta, where she founded the Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance, one of the longest-lasting lesbian feminist groups in the United States. Vicki then left Atlanta and has since spent over twenty years in Massachusetts. She has been legally married to her current partner since 2004. In 2009, Vicki received her Ph.D. in women's history from Union Institute, documenting her mother's involvement in Parent Teacher Association activism. Vicki has been published by Sojourner Truth Press and in Quest: A Feminist Quarterly, among other publications.
    This oral history has two components. Vicki first chronicles her life and experiences from childhood to coming out in Atlanta, Georgia. It is organized by both time and place, as Vicki describes what led her from Cornell, to Madison, to Atlanta, and finally to Massachusetts. She illustrates how her exposure to activism early in life informed and influenced her later participation in the labor rights movement and gay liberation. The second half of the oral history is topic-based. Vicki draws upon her experience with lesbian feminism to inform her opinions on the current LGBT marriage equality movement, parenthood, religion, and the aging gay and lesbian community.
    - Video interview of Vicki Gabriner
    - Transcript of interview of Vicki Gabriner (Box 1)
  - Emily Greene interviewed by Adrienne Szamotula, 2014 March 25; 1 oral histories